A young painter has a weird smell
coming out of his studio
When friends come to visit
they can barely breathe
The room smells like death Wait
are those actual human body parts
in his studio
Arms and legs
Is that a severed head
on the roof
It's Paris 1818
Napoleon has been gone
for three years
The Bourbon monarchy is back
The art world
is controlled by the Académie led
by David's star student Ingres
and a young artist
named Théodore Géricault
is working on something enormous
something that's going to make
Paris very uncomfortable
Tragically
he'd be dead at thirty two
but his friend also an artist
influenced by him would become
one of the key figures
of French romanticism
His name was Henri Delacroix
This is their story
The story of romantic art
אוקיי Last
time we left David in exile
the most powerful painter
in France banished to Brussels
for voting to kill a king
His student
Ingres was carrying the torch
of the neoclassical tradition
defending line reason
classical subjects
the whole program
mostly from Rome
where he'd been living for years
But the world had changed
Napoleon was gone
The old monarchies were back
And an entire generation
had grown up watching
the promises of the Enlightenment
that eighteenth-century belief
that reason and science
could answer everything collapse
Reason was supposed
to fix everything
It didn't
The Revolution was supposed
to bring liberty
It brought mass executions
Napoleon was supposed
to bring order
He brought 20 years of war
So a new generation
started asking
a different question
Not what is true
but what do I feel
That's romanticism
Not a style exactly
More like a shift in what matters
The Enlightenment
said Trust your mind
Romanticism said Trust your gut
your emotions your instincts
The things that
reason can't explain
It wasn't only painting
across music poetry
and philosophy
People were saying the same thing
Reason alone isn't enough
And in art
it starts with a concept
that the Romantics were obsessed
with a concept called the Sublime
The sublime is
Okay have you ever stood
at the edge of a cliff
or watched a thunderstorm
roll over the ocean
That feeling
where you're terrified
and amazed at the same time where
you feel tiny and overwhelmed
and somehow more alive
than you've ever been
That's the sublime
The Irish
British philosopher Edmund Burke
defined it in 1750 7
The experience of awe
mixed with terror in the face
of something vast powerful
or too big to grasp
The Romantics didn't want beauty
Beauty is pleasant
Beauty is a painting of a woman
on a swing
The Romantics wanted overwhelm
They wanted art
that made you feel like
you were standing at the edge
of something enormous
And one of the paintings
that captures it best is this one
Caspar David Friedrich
Wanderer above the Sea of Fog
painted around 1818
A man standing on a rocky peak
He's back to us
We can't see his face
We see what he sees
An infinite landscape
of fog and mountains
stretching to the horizon
He's alone completely alone
and the world
in front of him is beautiful
and terrifying and unknowable
That's Romanticism in one image
The individual
confronting the infinite
Friedrich was German
and Romanticism
wasn't just a French thing
Across Europe artists
were moving in this direction
In Britain J.M.W
Turner was doing something
similar
but in a completely different way
Where Friedrich is still
and quiet Turner is all motion
Storms fire light ships
dissolving into the air
His paintings don't ask
to be understood
They overwhelm you
Different approaches same idea
The individual facing forces
bigger than themselves
The romantic painter had a set
of obsessions big crush in nature
The individual lost
in something vast intense color
and dramatic light history myth
and far off places
Basically anything
that felt alive and untamed
compared to the gray routine
of modern Paris
that was the mood
and the painting
that truly announced romanticism
to the world
raw chaotic impossible to ignore
was about to arrive
June 18 16
A French warship
called the Meduse
is sailing to Senegal
On board soldiers settlers
the new colonial governor
And commanding the ship
a captain
named Hugo Duroy de Chaumareys
who had barely sailed
in 20 years
He got the job
through political connections
to the
newly restored Bourbon monarchy
He was by all accounts
spectacularly incompetent
After several days of sailing
not without some mistakes
and incidents
the Meduse got stuck
on a sandbank
off the coast of West Africa
And
there weren't enough lifeboats
So they built a raft hastily
out of whatever they could find
Around
150 people were loaded onto it
Soldiers sailors civilians
The raft was towed
behind the lifeboats
And then the tow ropes were cut
Whether it was deliberate
or accidental is still debated
but the result was the same
A hundred
and 40 7 people on a raft
barely above the waterline
set adrift in the open Atlantic
What followed over thirteen days
is one of the
most horrifying survival stories
in maritime history
By the second night
fights broke out
Men went mad
Some threw themselves
into the sea
By day 4 the survivals
began eating the dead
When the raft was
finally spotted by a passing ship
the Argus 13 days later
15 people were still alive
5 more died shortly after rescue
2 of the survivors Carriard
and Savigny published an account
It became a bestseller
and a political scandal
The incompetent captain was seen
as a symbol of everything wrong
with the restored monarchy
The government tried
to suppress the story
It didn't work
And a 27 year old painter
named Théodore Géricault
read that book
and became obsessed
What Géricault did next
is extraordinary even by well
by any standards
he tracked down the 2 survivors
interviewed them
had them sit for him
and describe everything:
the raft the bodies the weather
the moment they saw the ship
he built a scale model
of the raft in his studio
He went to the morgue repeatedly
and
brought back severed body parts
to study how dead flesh looks
He visited hospitals
to sketch the dying
His friends described the studio
as a slaughterhouse
The smell was unbreathable
he shaved his head
so he wouldn't be tempted
to go outside
He wanted no distractions
18 months
That's how long it took
and the result was a painting
roughly 16 by 23 and a half feet
The Raft of the Medusa 1819
At the bottom
the dead tangled gray
sliding into the water
A father holds his dead son
The bodies are not idealized
They're bloated discolored real
in the middle
the living barely exhausted
desperate clinging to each other
and to the raft
And at the top
a man waving a cloth
He's seen something
on the horizon
There that tiny speck
that's the Argus
That's rescue
It's so small you almost miss it
The entire painting
is built around that gap
between the desperate
waving figure and the almost
invisible ship between hope
and the very real possibility
that hope is an illusion
The ship might not see them
It might sail past
And everyone on this raft
will die
Géricault chose to paint
the most uncertain moment
Not the rescue not the suffering
in its worst the moment
where it could go either way
That's
not a neoclassical painting
There's no moral lesson
no ancient hero
no noble simplicity
It's a painting
about real people a real disaster
and the raw animal desperation
to survive
And it's painted at the scale
that the Académie
reserved for kings and myths
And look at how it's painted
Deep shadows dramatic light
cutting across the bodies
Géricault had studied Caravaggio
in Rome and you can feel it
The composition deliberately
echoes classical structures
a triangle like the Horatii
but it fills it with chaos
he used the old architecture
to hold together
something completely new
The Salon didn't know
what to do with it
The government was embarrassed
It was an attack
on their incompetence
Critics were divided
Géricault took the painting
to London
where it was a sensation
And then in 1824 he died
Years of horse riding injuries
left him bedridden his health
in collapse
He was 32 years old
If Géricault had lived
the whole story of Romanticism
might be different
But he didn't
The torch passed to his friend
a painter
who had watched the raft
being made from up close
who posed for one
of the dying figures in it and
who was about to take everything
Géricault had started and push it
further than anyone imagined
Eugene Delacroix was born in 1798
Officially his father
was Charles Delacroix a diplomat
But there's a problem
with that story
Charles had a medical condition
a massive tumor
that almost certainly left him
unable to father children
at the time Eugène was conceived
A rumor followed Delacroix
throughout his life that his real
father was Talleyrand
a powerful French diplomat
who had survived multiple regimes
by being exceptionally skilled
and adaptable
Delacroix was said
to look like Talleyrand
and it is rumored
that Talleyrand may have quietly
supported Delacroix's career but
nothing was ever confirmed
or denied
It is a great origin story
for a romantic painter
the illegitimate son of power
raised in its shadows destined
to rebel against everything
it stood for
His father died when he was 7
His mother when he was 16
By eighteen
he was essentially alone
in the world
Then he met Gericault
That friendship
changed everything
Both of them had studied
under the
painter Pierre Narcisse Gerard
a strict Neo classicist who gave
them a solid technical foundation
Gericault was older
and already pushing
against the rules
Delacroix watched him do it
When Géricault began working
on The Raft
of the Medusa Delacroix was close
to the process
He even posed
for one of the dying figures
Watching Géricault work
the research the intensity
the refusal to make
it comfortable or beautiful
left a mark on him
Not just a technical lesson
but a kind of permission
You could go this far
You could paint things like this
Delacroix's salon debut
came in 1822
He was 24
The Barque of Dante
Dante
and Virgil Crossing the River
Styx surrounded by the damned
The flesh of the
drowning figures is painted
with raw physical intensity
that shocked people
This wasn't
smooth polished surface of Ingres
It was nothing
like the calm idealized heroes
in David's paintings
This was paint that looked
like living flesh characters
showing intense emotion
This was new and different
2 years later he went bigger
The Massacre at Chios 1824
Based on a real event
Greek civilians
slaughtered by Ottoman troops
during the Greek War
of Independence
Look at the details
See how different it is
from any painting
we talked about
in the previous video
It's such a disturbing
intense scene
the painting is enormous brutal
and painted with a looseness
of brushwork
and emotional intensity
that made
the Académie deeply uncomfortable
One critic called it
The Massacre of Painting
Delacroix took it as a compliment
And 3 years later came
the painting
that really declared war
the painting that said
"I'm not David I'm not Ingres
I'm something else entirely."
the death of Sardanapalus
an Assyrian king
His empire is falling
His enemies are at the gates
and rather than surrender
he orders everything destroyed
His mistresses his horses
his treasures everything
He reclines on a massive red bed
and watches it all burn
Compare this to anything
David ever made
David controlled every inch
Rigid figures clean lines
each element in its place
This is a whirlpool
Bodies twist a horse
rears a woman is being stabbed
jewels cascade off the bed
And all of it the chaos
the movement
the drama is driven by color
Hot reds and golds
against cool shadow
No careful outline
holding it together
That was the provocation
Academic painting
emphasized drawing
first color second
Drawing was considered
the serious part
Color was just filling it in
Delacroix flipped it
And to Ingres that wasn't
just a different style
It challenged everything
painting was supposed to be
The Salon was horrified
Even Delacroix's supporters
were uneasy
This painting
nearly ended his career
It was too much too chaotic
too sensual too everything
Now let's finally
talk about the Delacroix-Ingres
rivalry
Because these
two were definitely not friends
And
it wasn't just a clash of ideals
There was real bad blood
between them
You remember Ingres
David's best student
who continued his legacy
the champion of line
and classical precision
He was still very much around
and he was very much not happy
about what Delacroix was doing
The camps were clear
Ingres
line drawing intellect restraint
the classical tradition
the Académie
Color paint emotion movement
independence
Ingres reportedly said
that Delacroix was an apostle
of ugliness and called him
a dangerous character
To Ingres Delacroix
wasn't just approaching painting
in the wrong way
He was threatening
the principles Ingres believed in
He was steering the art world
in the wrong direction
creating an unwelcome change
Ingres could not stand it
Delacroix
who was generally more diplomatic
in public criticized Ingres' art
in private writings
seeing it as overly controlled
and lacking life
They were once both appointed
to the same committee and had
to sit next to each other
Witnesses
said the tension was unbearable
But here's the thing
This wasn't petty
This was
a genuine philosophical war
about what art is for
Should a painting appeal
to your mind or to your gut
Should it teach you something
or make you feel something
Line versus color
Reason versus emotion
Ingres versus Delacroix
today we know that Inres' fear
of Delacroix destroying the rules
he protected was not for nothing
Delacroix did open
the door for change and after him
the art world saw many shifts
new and different ideas
of what art could be
Things that
neither Inre nor Delacroix
could even begin to imagine
but I'm getting ahead of myself
For now
we're still in 1830 France
the July Revolution
3 days of street fighting
in Paris
Barricades gunfire
Charles X
the last Bourbon king
was overthrown
A new more liberal monarchy
was installed
Delacroix wasn't a revolutionary
He wasn't David
He didn't join a political party
didn't vote
on anyone's execution
He was a moderate
But the spectacle of it
the energy the chaos
the bodies in the streets
moved him deeply
He wrote to his brother
"Since I have not fought
for the glory of my country
at least I will paint for her."
Liberty leading the people 1830
At the center Marianne
the female allegory of France
bare-breasted
holding the tricolor flag
striding forward
over the barricades
She's not a real woman
She's an idea
liberty itself made flesh
Besides her a boy with 2 pistols
He's maybe 12
He's terrified and excited
A man in a top hat
the middle class
A worker in a white shirt
a soldier
People of every class
and age fighting together
And at the bottom the dead lying
tangled half undressed the cost
Now I want you to compare this
to David's political paintings
David was a true believer
He joined the revolution
He voted
He signed warrants
His paintings were tools
of a specific political program
Delacroix didn't do any of that
He painted
the feeling of revolution
The light in his painting
is impossible
It's theatrical dramatic
not how a Paris street
actually looks during a battle
The composition is staged
Marianne is an allegory
not a real person
David painted ideology
Delacroix painted emotion
That might
be the clearest single way to
see the gap between Neoclassicism
and Romanticism
Not the only difference
but one of the deepest
Delacroix had found his voice
painting revolution
and myth in Paris
The next thing
that changed him completely
wouldn't come from Paris at all
In 1832
Delacroix got an invitation
that changed his life
France had sent an official
diplomatic mission to Morocco
and Delacroix was invited
to join as its artist
By this point
his name was significant enough
and his connections
in government circles deep enough
that having him among
carried its own prestige
France had also invaded Algeria
2 years earlier and the whole
trip was a colonial mission
Delacroix was traveling
under its protection
he went and it rewired his brain
He filled notebooks
with sketches watercolors
and notes
He was overwhelmed by the light
the color the architecture
the people
Everything looked different
from Paris
the light sharper the colors
stronger the streets
and people unlike anything
he had ever seen before
Women of Algiers
in their apartment 1834
Painted from memory after
Delacroix was given a rare access
to the private living quarters
of an Algerian household
3 women
in a richly decorated interior
a servant on the right
The colors are warm reds
golds deep greens
The light is soft
It's intimate
You feel like you're in the room
Picasso saw this painting
and was so obsessed with it
that he painted
around 15 variations of it
That's
how deep the influence goes
it's important to mention
that Delacroix
was genuinely fascinated by what
he saw in North Africa
His notebooks are detailed
respectful curious
He wasn't mocking or dismissive
But he was also a European man
traveling
under colonial protection
placing his own fantasies
onto a culture that was
being colonized by his country
The real North Africa
with its own history
its own complexity
complexity was more complicated
than what he painted
This tension
between genuine fascination
and placing your own ideas
onto another culture
is something we'll come back
to later in the series when
we talk about Gauguin in Tahiti
Delacroix is the early
relatively gentle version
of a pattern
that gets much more troubling
later
Women of Algiers
holds both things at once
The painting is extraordinary
The color the warmth
the sense of actually being
inside that room
And it's also a fantasy
a beautiful partial fantasy
made by someone
who had the power to walk in
and the freedom to decide
what it all meant
that doesn't make the painting
less beautiful
It makes the beauty more complicated
North Africa had changed Delacroix's color
his sense of light
his whole way of seeing
Back in Paris one man a poet
understood exactly what had happened
and why it mattered
His name was Charles Baudelaire
In 1846 he wrote a salon review
with
one of the sharpest definitions
of Romanticism ever put on paper
Romanticism is precisely situated
neither in choice of subjects
nor in exact truth
but in a mode of feeling
Not what you paint
not how accurately
but the feeling it creates
Baudelaire praised Delacroix
for decades
calling him the most suggestive
of all painters
Delacroix spent his later years
on major government commissions
Murals at the Palais Bourbon
the Luxembourg Palace
the Chapel of the Holy Angels
at Saint-Sulpice
this might seem surprising
for a painter who had spent years
shocking the Salon but government
commissions work differently
A minister could hire
whoever he chose and by the 1830s
Delacroix was too famous
to keep ignoring
Liberty Leading the People
had helped
however uncomfortable the salon
found his style that painting
had made him a national figure
his late work gets looser freer
almost abstract
The individual brush strokes
become visible
You stop seeing the subject
and start seeing the paint itself
You can see in those murals
the seeds of what's coming next
Impressionism even abstraction
His health declined
through the 1850s
Tuberculosis
He died on August 13th 1863
in Paris
His studio and notebooks
contained
thousands of works studies
sketches finished paintings
And here's the detail
that matters
His funeral was attended
by several of the young painters
who would go on
and become the Impressionists
Bazille was there
Monet and Renoir likely were too
They admired him
They saw in his color
his freedom his refusal to submit
to the Académie's rules
a path forward
Delacroix didn't know it
but he was handing the torch
to the next generation
So here's
where Romanticism leaves us
It said "Feel everything
The mind isn't enough
Reason isn't enough
Art should overwhelm you
with beauty with terror
with passion with the sublime."
And it delivered
Géricault's The Raft
of the Medusa is overwhelming
Delacroix's Liberty
Leading the People
is electrifying
Turner's The Burning
of the Houses of Lords
and Commons is staggering
Friedrich's Wanderer is sublime
But there is a risk
If you chase feeling
if you abandon the rules
where do you stop
Romanticism opened a door
that couldn't be closed
What kind of art can be made
when you stop following
the Académie's guidelines
remember the Salon's hierarchy
of subjects what was considered
the most noble and
what sat at the very bottom
of the accepted list
of painting topics
can you imagine what
kind of art could be made when
all of those rules are rejected
What kind of new creative
even crazy ideas
could come into the world
There is still so much more
to come
But for now
let's continue with this
What if instead of painting gods
and heroes and revolutions
and fantasies you just looked
What if you painted the world
exactly as it was not
as you wished it was not
as it made you feel
Just what's there
The ugly parts
the boring parts reality
as it is
what if you painted a funeral
in a small town
with ugly people and a dog but
at the size of a history painting
What if
you built your own exhibition
hall when the salon rejected you
and you told the entire art
establishment to go to hell
One man did exactly that
His name was Gustave Courbet
He was a loud arrogant
brilliant troublemaker and
he pissed off a lot of people
in 19th century Paris
That's next time
Bye