In his left hand, a letter.
Corday, Marat's murderer,
did use a letter
to get into the apartment,
but this isn't that letter.
David wrote those words himself.
They make
Marat look like a man killed
while helping someone in need.
David put it in his hand
on purpose as part of the myth
he was building.
On the floor, the knife, bloodied,
and on the wooden block
besides the bath,
the block Marat used as a desk,
David carved 2 words.
To Marat from David.
He signed the painting into the painting.
It's a dedication, a memorial,
and a political act.
Now, here's what I need you
to sit with.
This painting is propaganda.
It absolutely is.
David has taken a man
who was, by many accounts, paranoid, cruel,
and responsive for stirring up mob violence
And turned him into a saint.
The bath is clean, the body idealized.
The composition is borrowed directly
from Christian art, specifically the Pietà,
which is a famous image
of Mary holding the body of Jesus.
You know this Michelangelo's famous sculpture?
Do you see it?
That arrangement, that specific quality of grief
held perfectly still.
David took it and transplanted it into a bathtub in Paris.
Marat as the Revolution's crucified Christ.
David made this painting
to serve the revolution,
to turn a murderer
into a martyr,
to make
you feel something specific, grief, outrage, devotion
to the cause.
It's propaganda and it's a masterpiece.
Both are true at the same time,
and that tension
is what makes David so important
and so unsettling.
He painted virtue. He preached sacrifice. And he signed the warrants that sent people to die.
The revolution gave David everything: power, purpose,
a reason to paint
Now, it was about
to take it all back.
It couldn't last.
The revolution, like all revolutions,
started eating its own.
On July 27th, 1794, Robespierre,
the radical Jacobin leader, was overthrown, arrested,
executed the next day, and soon
after, they came for David.
He was arrested, imprisoned.
He came very close
to the guillotine himself, the same guillotine
he had helped send others to.
His students lobbied for his release.
It took months.
And in prison, he did something remarkable.
He painted himself not as a hero,
not as a martyr,
not as someone Roman or Greek,
just himself.
A middle-aged man with a swollen cheek.
he had a facial tumor
that distorted his features.
Holding a palette, looking out at you
with an expression that's hard to read.
Surprise?
Confusion?
Honesty?
It might be the most intimate thing
he ever painted
because it wasn't for anyone.
It wasn't for the salon
or for the revolution.
It was just a man
in a cell looking at himself.
And don't ask me
how he got painting materials in prison.
After his release,
he said he had been deceived
by the mask of patriotism.
Was he?
Was he really deceived,
or was he just saying
what he needed to say to survive?
That's one of the great unanswerable questions
about David, and I think
the answer might be both.
He was a true believer
who was also very good in surviving.
People are complicated.
And then he met Napoleon.
It was 1797.
Napoleon was a young general, already famous,
already radiating that kind of charisma
that makes painter reach for their brushes.
David met him and wrote,
Oh, my friends,
what a beautiful head he has.
It is pure, it is great.
It is as beautiful as the antique.
As beautiful as the antique.
There it is again.
David looked at a living, breathing military
commander and saw a Greek statue.
He couldn't help himself.
And Napoleon, a master of image
and spectacle, saw in David
exactly what he needed.
The greatest painter of his time, ready
to turn him into a living legend.
Okay.Napoleon crossing the Alps, 1801.
You know this image.
Even if
you never been into an art museum,
you know this image.
Napoleon on a rearing
white horse, cape flowing, arm pointing
forward, the names of Hannibal and Charlemagne
carved into the rocks below him,
As if to say
he belongs among them.
I've seen this painting in person,
and the first thing
that hits you is the scale.
If you see it on a screen,
it's completely different from how
people back at the time felt when
they saw it in front of them.
Like, this painting is about this size,
you just stand
in front of it, and you feel
that you're looking at something amazing.
I can't explain it.
You, you have to experience it,
'cause I was really surprised
to feel that way.
Okay, back to the story.
The painting is huge.
You stand in front of it, and
you feel small, which is, of course,
exactly the point.
Napoleon
asked to be painted calm
on a spirited horse.
David delivered.
Here's the thing, though.
The real crossing was difficult, cold,
and unglamorous.
Napoleon rode a mule for much
of it, led by a local guide.
David wasn't painting what happened.
He was painting
what Napoleon wanted to believe about himself.
The heroic version.
The myth.
Nobody remembers the mule.
Everyone remembers this.
And then there's the coronation.
1805 to 1807.
Over 30 feet wide.
Napoleon crowning Josephine at Notre Dame,
surrounded by hundreds of figures.
David was there in person,
sketching the ceremony.
But he rearranged reality.
Look, see that woman in the balcony?
That's Napoleon's mother, Leticia.
She's prominently placed, watching proudly.
Except she wasn't there.
She refused to come.
David painted her in anyway
because Napoleon wanted her there.
The painting isn't a record
of what happened.
It's a record
of what should have happened
According to the man in charge.
After Napoleon's final defeat in 1815,
the Bourbon monarchy was restored, and
they had a long memory.
David had voted to execute their king
in 1793.
That was 22 years ago.
They hadn't forgotten.
He was exiled, banned from France
as a king killer.
He moved to Brussels and kept painting,
but the work got softer, less urgent.
The fire was going out.
He died in Brussels
on December 29th, 1825,
at the age of 77.
France refused
to allow his body to return.
The man who had
been the most powerful artist
in the country,
who had shaped the visual identity
of the revolution, of Napoleon,
of an entire era,
was buried in a foreign city.
He's still there.
So, what did
David leave behind?
A movement, a set of rules,
and an institution, the Académie Royale,
that would enforce those rules
for the next 50 years.
His greatest student, Ingres,
became the guardian of that legacy.
He spent his entire career
defending classical drawing, insisting that discipline
and line were the foundation of everything.
The Académie backed him.
For decades, the world David built held.
So here's
where I want to leave you.
David understood something fundamental about images.
They aren't just decoration, they're arguments.
A painting can make you believe something.
It can make an idea
feel noble, inevitable, even heroic.
his style
helped make that power possible
The clean lines, the stark compositions,
the restrained, controlled color.
Everything is clear, deliberate, and serious.
Nothing is accidental.
The paintings feel certain
about what they are saying,
and that certainty is persuasive.
And the images themself did real work.
The Oath of the Horatii
didn't just show Roman virtue,
it presented a model
of duty and sacrifice.
The Death of Marat didn't simply show
a political killing, it transformed Marat
into a martyr of the revolution.
Napoleon crossing the Alps
didn't document an event. It constructed Napoleon's image of leadership.
That’s David’s real legacy. Not just a style, and not only a school of followers but a demonstration of how powerful images can shape political imagination.
But the more interesting part
of David's story isn't the propaganda,
it's the man behind it.
David painted virtue, duty, and sacrifice,
and he seemed to have genuinely believe
in those ideals.
At the same time,
he lived at the center of power
during one of the most violent
and chaotic periods in French history.
That combination was rare.
An artist who wasn't just observing events,
but helping shape how
they were seen and remembered.
And that may be
what makes him so remarkable.
Not just a great painter,
but an artist
whose images helped define an era.
But not everyone accepted
what David had built
Not everyone thought paintings
should be lessons in virtue
or that reason should rule everything art
could be.
One painter born in seventeen ninety-eight,
just a few years after the Terror,
the revolution's most violent period,
was about
to blow the whole thing up.
Was about to blow the whole thing
up with color, with chaos,
with a trip to North Africa
that changed the way he saw everything.
His name was Eugène Delacroix,
and his story starts
with a shipwreck, a madman,
and a raft full of corpses.
That's next time.
ביי.