Okay.
Imagine this.
It's January 21st, 1793.
France is 4 years into a revolution.
The monarchy has collapsed.
The church has been dismantled.
The old aristocratic order, gone.
The country is trying to build itself
from scratch, and nobody is quite sure
it's going to work.
You're in Paris,
sitting in the National Convention,
the new revolutionary parliament,
and a vote is being taken.
Should the King of France
be put to death?
now, the room
is full of politicians, lawyers, revolutionaries,
but sitting amongst them, voting,
is a painter, the most famous painter
in France, a man
whose paintings hang in the Louvre,
whose work has made grown men
weep in public.
And when his name is called,
he stands up,
and he votes yes.
He votes to kill the king.
His name was Jacques-Louis David,
and that vote, a painter
voting on the life of a king,
would define everything that came after,
For better and for worse.
But to understand how he got there,
we first need to ask:
How does a painter ends up
with that kind of power?
To understand that, we need
to go way back before David,
before the revolution, back to a time
when French art looked very different.
how do
you pronounce the name?
Jean-Honoré Fragonard.
Jean-Honoré Fra-Fragonard.
Look at this painting, The Swing
by Jean-Honoré Fragonard, 1767.
A woman swings her shoe,
flying toward the little angel
who gestures shh
to show a secret is unfolding.
A man hides in the bushes,
looking up her skirt
while the older man pushes the swing,
unaware of what's happening.
This painting is witty, flirtatious,
and entirely wrapped up
in the private pleasures
of the ruling class.
And the French aristocracy loved this stuff.
This was the art
of the ruling class.
Rococo, they called it. Light,
decorative, charming, sexy.
Say Boucher.
Painters like Boucher and Fragonard
made a fortune painting exactly this.
Beautiful people doing beautiful things
in beautiful gardens.
But by the 1760s,
not everyone was charmed.
The critic Denis Diderot,
one of the sharpest minds in France,
looked at Boucher's paintings
and wrote.
What colors, what variety,
what a wealth of objects and ideas.
This man has everything except truth.
Except truth.
That's the key word,
because underneath all that silk and powder,
France was rottingThe monarchy was broke,
the peasants were starving, and the art,
the officials celebrated expensive art
was paintings of aristocrats on swings.
It couldn't last.
And right around this time something happened
that changed the direction of European culture.
They dug up Pompeii.
well, first Herculaneum in 1730
8, then Pompeii in 1740 8.
2 entire Roman cities
buried by a volcano
in 70 9 AD, suddenly visible again.
And it wasn't just columns
and statues, it was everything.
Houses, wall paintings,
furniture, graffiti, bread still in the ovens.
An entire civilization frozen in time.
And among the educated,
wealthy classes of Europe, this sparked
a kind of ancient world mania.
Greek furniture, Roman architecture,
cl-classical hairstyles.
If you were a wealthy young man,
you went on the Grand Tour.
You traveled to Rome,
you sketched the ruins, you came back,
and you told everyone
how cultured you were.
It was the 18th century version
of studying abroad
and making it your whole personality
But the person who turned this obsession
into a complete theory, the person
who gave the educated classes of Europe
a framework for why ancient Greece
was the peak of human achievement,
was a man who never
painted a single painting.
Not a painter, not an architect,
a writer, a critic.
His name was John Joachim Winckelmann.
Winckelmann was born in 1717 in Prussia
His father was a shoemaker, dirt
poor, but the kid was brilliant.
Taught himself Greek and Latin,
worked as a school teacher
and a librarian just to survive,
and in 1755, he published a book
that changed everything.
It was called Thoughts
on the Imitation of Greek Works
in Painting and Sculpture, and in it,
he made the claim that would echo
for the next hundred years.
He said that the defining quality
of Greek art was...
noble simplicity and quiet grandeur.
5 words.
That's it.
5 words that defined
an entire century of art.
What did he mean?
He meant that great art
should be calm, restrained, balanced.
Not screaming, no drama, no excess.
Think of a Greek statue.
Perfect proportions, calm expression,
idealized body, pure white marble.
That, Winckelmann said, was the peak.
Everything else was step down.
one small problem
with this, the ancient Greeks
did not make pure white marble statues.
Their statues were painted
vivid, garnished colors, bright red lips,
blue eyes, yellow hair.
We only know this now
from chemical analysis
and faint traces of pigment.
Winckelmann had no idea.
He built an entire aesthetic philosophy
around the wrong thing.
His idea of noble simplicity
was, at least in part,
the result of 2,000 years
of paint wearing off, which is
either a great argument
for the power of an idea
or a cautionary tale
about inventing a perfect past
to criticize an imperfect present.
He moved to Rome, got access
to the greatest collections of ancient art
in the world, and in 1764
published History of the Art of Antiquity,
which transformed the discipline of art history.
People had written about individual artists
before, but Winckelmann organized everything around styles
and periods, tracing the rise and fall
of entire civilizations through their art.
That framework, we still use it today
Now here's the thing
and this is important
Winckelmann never went to Greece.
His entire philosophy of Greek art
was based on Roman copies.
He was building a fantasy of Greece
from secondhand evidence, and he did it
so convincingly that everyone believed him.
He was murdered in 1760 8
in Trieste
at the age of 50,
stabbed by a man he'd met
in an inn
The circumstances suggest a sexual encounter
gone wrong.
Winckelmann's letters express intense romantic feelings
toward young men,
and most scholars read him as gay.
Though, as with so
much of his life, certainty
is hard to come by.
What we can say
is it adds another layer
to his lifelong idealization
of the male Greek body.
What matters for us is
this, Winckelmann created the idea.
He built the intellectual framework.
Now, someone needed
to turn it into paintings.
but first you need
to understand how the art
world actually worked in 17th century France,
because it was a system,
rigid, hierarchical, and brutally competitive.
There was one exhibition
that mattered above all others,
the Salon run by the Académie Royale,
held at the Louvre.
If you got into the Salon,
you had a career.
There were other patrons, other venues,
but nothing with the Salon's reach, prestige,
or power.
To be excluded from the Salon
was to be invisible.
And within the salon
there was a strict hierarchy
of what you were allowed to paint.
At the top, history paintings, scenes
from the Bible, from mythology,
from ancient history,
the noblest form of art.
And at the very bottom, still life.
This hierarchy matters.
It explains everything about what's coming.
It explains why
David painted Greek heroes.
The other thing
you need to know about
is the Prix de Rome,
the most prestigious prize
a young artist could win.
you win the Prix de Rome,
you get a funded trip
to the French Academy in Rome.
Years of studying the masters,
the ruins, the sculpture.
And a young painter named Jacques-Louis David
wanted it more than everything.
He failed 3 times.