David was born in Paris, 1748.
His father was killed in a duel
when David was very young,
so already we're starting with violence.
Dead parent before age 10.
Every great origin story has one.
He was raised by well-off uncles
who wanted him to be an architect.
He wanted to paint.
he studied
under a painter named Joseph Marie Vien,
and
he entered the Prix de Rome competition
multiple times through the early 1770s.
He lost.
He entered again, lost again.
He entered a third time, lost again.
And repeated failure broke him.
According to some biographical accounts,
David locked himself in his room
and refused to eat,
convinced his life was over.
The details are murky
and probably exaggerated by later admirers,
but the despair was real.
he was in his mid twenties,
and the one path he staked everything
on kept closing in his face.
He entered again in 1774.
He didn't win.
Just kidding.
He finally got it.
He went to Rome and everything changed.
He arrived in Rome,
and at first wasn't very impressed,
struggling to find his direction.
But soon, the ideas he read about,
especially those of Winckelmann,
the art critic, came to life
in front of him.
He studied ancient sculptures, Raphael
and artists like Caravaggio,
spending 5 years learning
and absorbing the art around him.
And when he came back to Paris,
he was a completely different painter.
The loose, colorful style
of his early work was gone.
In its place, moral seriousness,
clean lines, rigid geometry, local colors,
and a restrained palette, muted overall
with sharp accents
guiding the viewer's eyes.
Ancient virtue painted with absolute conviction.
He had become exactly what Winckelmann
the theorist had called for.
He had become neoclassical.
Worth noting, David wasn't alone in this.
Across Europe, artists adopted the neoclassical style
to explore ideas of beauty, harmony,
and timeless order
inspired by ancient Greece and Rome.
Painters used classical myths and historical scenes
to explore heroism, virtue, and human emotion.
Sculptures like Canova focused on elegance
of the human body, calm, idealized forms
in perfect proportions.
The style appeared in mythological paintings,
portraits, architecture, decorative arts.
It became a visual language
of elegance and good taste.
David worked in the same tradition
as all of these artists, but what
he did was charge the style
with moral and political urgency,
and
you can see the difference immediately.
His first big Salon success
was Belisarius Begging for Alms in 1781.
A Roman general, once great, now blind
and begging in the street.
The message?
Even the greatest can be destroyed
by an ungrateful state.
People noticed.
Success
at the Salon made David
a full member of the Académie Royale,
the institute that trained French artists,
set official standards,
and decided what counted as serious painting.
He became
one of its most powerful teachers.
His style, his values,
his way of seeing passed
directly into the next generation.
He wasn't just working within the system,
he was shaping it.
But the painting
that changed everything, the work
that defined Neoclassicism came 3 years later.
This is The Oath of the Horatii.
David painted it in 1784.
Take a moment
and really look at it.
3 brothers, the Horatii,
are swearing an oath.
They're about to fight to the death
for Rome against 3 brothers
for a rival city.
Their father holds the swords.
The brothers reach for them.
Their bodies are taugh, geometric, almost architectural.
They're not individuals.
They're a machine,
a machine built for duty.
Look at the colors.
The brothers wear brighter, more saturated reds.
Your eye goes to them first,
and it's supposed to.
The women on the right
are painted softer, muted tones, blues, grays,
near white.
The color itself tells you
the moral structure
before you even understood what's happening.
Action and duty on the left, grief
and passivity on the right.
The stone background
is all natural browns and grays,
keeping your attention on the figures.
The colors are clean, flat,
and clearly separated.
Every form is clear and deliberate.
Notice also the light.
Harsh, directional, almost theatrical,
like a spotlight on a stage
In the composition,
your eye is drawn to the center,
to the swords, the literal pivot point
between duty and loss.
The whole thing is controlled,
deliberate, organized, the opposite of Rococo
in every possible way.
And then look at the right side
of the painting, the woman.
They're collapsed, weeping, because here's the thing.
One of the Horatii brothers
is married to a woman
from the enemy city.
She's actually the sister
of one of the enemy brothers,
and one of the enemy brothers
is engaged to a Horatii sister.
No matter who wins,
these women lose someone they love.
The men are rigid, vertical,
all straight lines.
The women are curved, soft, crumbling.
Duty on the left, grief
on the right, and the swords
in the center.
The message is brutal and clear.
Duty to the state comes before everything,
before love, before family,
before your own life.
When this painting was exhibited
at the salon,
people wept in front of it.
Not just because it was sad,
because it was powerful.
It felt like a call to action.
And David didn't stop.
In 1780 7, The Death of Socrates.
Socrates, condemned by the Athenian state
for his ideas,
calmly
reaching for the cup of poison
while his students fall apart around him.
The state is killing him,
and he accepts it with perfect calm.
You die for what you believe.
And then, in 1780 9,
the lictors bring to Brutus
the bodies of his sons.
Brutus, the founder of the Roman Republic,
has ordered the execution
of his own sons
for conspiring to restore the monarchy
The bodies are being carried past him.
He doesn't look.
The women scream.
He sits in shadow,
rigid, destroyed, but unbroken.
This painting was displayed at the Salon
just weeks after the storming
of the Bastille.
The Paris prison was attacked
in July 1789,
marked the beginning of the French Revolution.
The story goes that authorities tried
to pull it from the exhibition,
but the crowd demanded it to stay.
whether that happened
exactly as described is debated.
Some historians think
the tale was polished later
to make David seem more heroically embattled.
Regardless, the painting's timing was explosive.
Do you see what's happening?
These aren't just paintings anymore.
A painting about a man
who killed his sons
to protect the Republic, displayed in Paris
in summer of 1789?
That's not art appreciation.
That's a political statement, and
everyone in that room knew it.
David had spent a decade
painting ancient heroes
who sacrificed everything for the state,
and now, in the summer of
1789, the state was being torn apart
and rebuilt.
And David wasn't going
to just paint it,
he was going to join it.
This is where the story goes dark,
and I mean genuinely dark.
Not art world drama dark.
People dying dark.
In 1792, David was elected
to the National Convention, the revolutionary parliament.
He didn't sit with the moderates.
He sat with the Montagrats,
the radicals, the Jacobins.
They were led
by Maximilian Robespierre, the lawyer
who made himself the ideological heart
of the revolution
and who was rapidly becoming
its most feared figure.
And on January twenty-first, seventeen ninety-three,
the day I mentioned
at the beginning,
David voted
for the execution of King Louis XVI.
A painter voted to kill a king.
But he didn't stop there.
David became essentially the revolution's visual authority.
He organized festivals, massive public events meant
to replace Catholic ritual with republican ceremony.
He contributed to the design of uniforms
and public imagery.
He was deeply involved
in shaping what the revolution looked like,
and in a world before photography,
before television,
that meant he had real influence
over what people believed about it.
He was close to Robespierre,
the radical Jacobin leader.
Very close.
He reportedly said to him,
"If you drink hemlock,
I will drink it with you."
That's not a casual friendship.
That's a pact.
He was actively involved
in the revolutionary government,
sitting on the Committee of General Security,
putting his name on documents
that led to people being arrested, tried, and executed.
was
one of many people
who signed, not acting alone,
but consider what that means
for the man
who painted the death of Socrates.
You remember that painting, Socrates
in his last moments,
calmly reaching for the cup of poison
while his students fall apart around him?
Socrates was condemned by the Athenian state
for refusing to abandon his ideas.
That's the subject David chose to paint
and made beautiful,
a man killed by the state.
And now, David was the state.
His name was on the paperwork.
The tension between the ideals he painted
and the reality he served is staggering.
In July 1793, a shocking event
in revolutionary Paris gave rise to
one of the century's most famous paintings.
Jean-Paul Marat was a revolutionary journalist,
a radical.
He had a skin condition
that forced him to spend hours
in a medicinal bath,
where he would write, receive visitors,
and conduct business.
On July 13th, 1793,
a young woman named Charlotte Corday
talked her way into his apartment,
claiming to have information about counter-revolutionary plots.
Marat received her
while sitting in his bath.
She pulled out a knife
and stabbed him in the chest.
He died almost immediately.
According to accounts
that have been passed down,
though some historians treat this with caution,
David had visited Marat
the day before.
He knew the bath,
the setup, the man,
and when he heard the news,
he went to work immediately.
Look at it.
Marat is slumped in his bath.
His head is wrapped in a cloth.
His skin is pale, almost glowing.
His face is calm, peaceful.
He looks like he's sleeping.
He looks like Christ
taken down from the cross.
But I'll get to that
in a sec.