Okay.
Imagine this.
It's January 21st, 1793.
France is 4 years into a revolution.
The monarchy has collapsed.
The church has been dismantled.
The old aristocratic order, gone.
The country is trying to build itself
from scratch, and nobody is quite sure
it's going to work.
You're in Paris,
sitting in the National Convention,
the new revolutionary parliament,
and a vote is being taken.
Should the King of France
be put to death?
now, the room
is full of politicians, lawyers, revolutionaries,
but sitting amongst them, voting,
is a painter, the most famous painter
in France, a man
whose paintings hang in the Louvre,
whose work has made grown men
weep in public.
And when his name is called,
he stands up,
and he votes yes.
He votes to kill the king.
His name was Jacques-Louis David,
and that vote, a painter
voting on the life of a king,
would define everything that came after,
For better and for worse.
But to understand how he got there,
we first need to ask:
How does a painter ends up
with that kind of power?
To understand that, we need
to go way back before David,
before the revolution, back to a time
when French art looked very different.
how do
you pronounce the name?
Jean-Honoré Fragonard.
Jean-Honoré Fra-Fragonard.
Look at this painting, The Swing
by Jean-Honoré Fragonard, 1767.
A woman swings her shoe,
flying toward the little angel
who gestures shh
to show a secret is unfolding.
A man hides in the bushes,
looking up her skirt
while the older man pushes the swing,
unaware of what's happening.
This painting is witty, flirtatious,
and entirely wrapped up
in the private pleasures
of the ruling class.
And the French aristocracy loved this stuff.
This was the art
of the ruling class.
Rococo, they called it. Light,
decorative, charming, sexy.
Say Boucher.
Painters like Boucher and Fragonard
made a fortune painting exactly this.
Beautiful people doing beautiful things
in beautiful gardens.
But by the 1760s,
not everyone was charmed.
The critic Denis Diderot,
one of the sharpest minds in France,
looked at Boucher's paintings
and wrote.
What colors, what variety,
what a wealth of objects and ideas.
This man has everything except truth.
Except truth.
That's the key word,
because underneath all that silk and powder,
France was rottingThe monarchy was broke,
the peasants were starving, and the art,
the officials celebrated expensive art
was paintings of aristocrats on swings.
It couldn't last.
And right around this time something happened
that changed the direction of European culture.
They dug up Pompeii.
well, first Herculaneum in 1730
8, then Pompeii in 1740 8.
2 entire Roman cities
buried by a volcano
in 70 9 AD, suddenly visible again.
And it wasn't just columns
and statues, it was everything.
Houses, wall paintings,
furniture, graffiti, bread still in the ovens.
An entire civilization frozen in time.
And among the educated,
wealthy classes of Europe, this sparked
a kind of ancient world mania.
Greek furniture, Roman architecture,
cl-classical hairstyles.
If you were a wealthy young man,
you went on the Grand Tour.
You traveled to Rome,
you sketched the ruins, you came back,
and you told everyone
how cultured you were.
It was the 18th century version
of studying abroad
and making it your whole personality
But the person who turned this obsession
into a complete theory, the person
who gave the educated classes of Europe
a framework for why ancient Greece
was the peak of human achievement,
was a man who never
painted a single painting.
Not a painter, not an architect,
a writer, a critic.
His name was John Joachim Winckelmann.
Winckelmann was born in 1717 in Prussia
His father was a shoemaker, dirt
poor, but the kid was brilliant.
Taught himself Greek and Latin,
worked as a school teacher
and a librarian just to survive,
and in 1755, he published a book
that changed everything.
It was called Thoughts
on the Imitation of Greek Works
in Painting and Sculpture, and in it,
he made the claim that would echo
for the next hundred years.
He said that the defining quality
of Greek art was...
noble simplicity and quiet grandeur.
5 words.
That's it.
5 words that defined
an entire century of art.
What did he mean?
He meant that great art
should be calm, restrained, balanced.
Not screaming, no drama, no excess.
Think of a Greek statue.
Perfect proportions, calm expression,
idealized body, pure white marble.
That, Winckelmann said, was the peak.
Everything else was step down.
one small problem
with this, the ancient Greeks
did not make pure white marble statues.
Their statues were painted
vivid, garnished colors, bright red lips,
blue eyes, yellow hair.
We only know this now
from chemical analysis
and faint traces of pigment.
Winckelmann had no idea.
He built an entire aesthetic philosophy
around the wrong thing.
His idea of noble simplicity
was, at least in part,
the result of 2,000 years
of paint wearing off, which is
either a great argument
for the power of an idea
or a cautionary tale
about inventing a perfect past
to criticize an imperfect present.
He moved to Rome, got access
to the greatest collections of ancient art
in the world, and in 1764
published History of the Art of Antiquity,
which transformed the discipline of art history.
People had written about individual artists
before, but Winckelmann organized everything around styles
and periods, tracing the rise and fall
of entire civilizations through their art.
That framework, we still use it today
Now here's the thing
and this is important
Winckelmann never went to Greece.
His entire philosophy of Greek art
was based on Roman copies.
He was building a fantasy of Greece
from secondhand evidence, and he did it
so convincingly that everyone believed him.
He was murdered in 1760 8
in Trieste
at the age of 50,
stabbed by a man he'd met
in an inn
The circumstances suggest a sexual encounter
gone wrong.
Winckelmann's letters express intense romantic feelings
toward young men,
and most scholars read him as gay.
Though, as with so
much of his life, certainty
is hard to come by.
What we can say
is it adds another layer
to his lifelong idealization
of the male Greek body.
What matters for us is
this, Winckelmann created the idea.
He built the intellectual framework.
Now, someone needed
to turn it into paintings.
but first you need
to understand how the art
world actually worked in 17th century France,
because it was a system,
rigid, hierarchical, and brutally competitive.
There was one exhibition
that mattered above all others,
the Salon run by the Académie Royale,
held at the Louvre.
If you got into the Salon,
you had a career.
There were other patrons, other venues,
but nothing with the Salon's reach, prestige,
or power.
To be excluded from the Salon
was to be invisible.
And within the salon
there was a strict hierarchy
of what you were allowed to paint.
At the top, history paintings, scenes
from the Bible, from mythology,
from ancient history,
the noblest form of art.
And at the very bottom, still life.
This hierarchy matters.
It explains everything about what's coming.
It explains why
David painted Greek heroes.
The other thing
you need to know about
is the Prix de Rome,
the most prestigious prize
a young artist could win.
you win the Prix de Rome,
you get a funded trip
to the French Academy in Rome.
Years of studying the masters,
the ruins, the sculpture.
And a young painter named Jacques-Louis David
wanted it more than everything.
He failed 3 times.
David was born in Paris, 1748.
His father was killed in a duel
when David was very young,
so already we're starting with violence.
Dead parent before age 10.
Every great origin story has one.
He was raised by well-off uncles
who wanted him to be an architect.
He wanted to paint.
he studied
under a painter named Joseph Marie Vien,
and
he entered the Prix de Rome competition
multiple times through the early 1770s.
He lost.
He entered again, lost again.
He entered a third time, lost again.
And repeated failure broke him.
According to some biographical accounts,
David locked himself in his room
and refused to eat,
convinced his life was over.
The details are murky
and probably exaggerated by later admirers,
but the despair was real.
he was in his mid twenties,
and the one path he staked everything
on kept closing in his face.
He entered again in 1774.
He didn't win.
Just kidding.
He finally got it.
He went to Rome and everything changed.
He arrived in Rome,
and at first wasn't very impressed,
struggling to find his direction.
But soon, the ideas he read about,
especially those of Winckelmann,
the art critic, came to life
in front of him.
He studied ancient sculptures, Raphael
and artists like Caravaggio,
spending 5 years learning
and absorbing the art around him.
And when he came back to Paris,
he was a completely different painter.
The loose, colorful style
of his early work was gone.
In its place, moral seriousness,
clean lines, rigid geometry, local colors,
and a restrained palette, muted overall
with sharp accents
guiding the viewer's eyes.
Ancient virtue painted with absolute conviction.
He had become exactly what Winckelmann
the theorist had called for.
He had become neoclassical.
Worth noting, David wasn't alone in this.
Across Europe, artists adopted the neoclassical style
to explore ideas of beauty, harmony,
and timeless order
inspired by ancient Greece and Rome.
Painters used classical myths and historical scenes
to explore heroism, virtue, and human emotion.
Sculptures like Canova focused on elegance
of the human body, calm, idealized forms
in perfect proportions.
The style appeared in mythological paintings,
portraits, architecture, decorative arts.
It became a visual language
of elegance and good taste.
David worked in the same tradition
as all of these artists, but what
he did was charge the style
with moral and political urgency,
and
you can see the difference immediately.
His first big Salon success
was Belisarius Begging for Alms in 1781.
A Roman general, once great, now blind
and begging in the street.
The message?
Even the greatest can be destroyed
by an ungrateful state.
People noticed.
Success
at the Salon made David
a full member of the Académie Royale,
the institute that trained French artists,
set official standards,
and decided what counted as serious painting.
He became
one of its most powerful teachers.
His style, his values,
his way of seeing passed
directly into the next generation.
He wasn't just working within the system,
he was shaping it.
But the painting
that changed everything, the work
that defined Neoclassicism came 3 years later.
This is The Oath of the Horatii.
David painted it in 1784.
Take a moment
and really look at it.
3 brothers, the Horatii,
are swearing an oath.
They're about to fight to the death
for Rome against 3 brothers
for a rival city.
Their father holds the swords.
The brothers reach for them.
Their bodies are taugh, geometric, almost architectural.
They're not individuals.
They're a machine,
a machine built for duty.
Look at the colors.
The brothers wear brighter, more saturated reds.
Your eye goes to them first,
and it's supposed to.
The women on the right
are painted softer, muted tones, blues, grays,
near white.
The color itself tells you
the moral structure
before you even understood what's happening.
Action and duty on the left, grief
and passivity on the right.
The stone background
is all natural browns and grays,
keeping your attention on the figures.
The colors are clean, flat,
and clearly separated.
Every form is clear and deliberate.
Notice also the light.
Harsh, directional, almost theatrical,
like a spotlight on a stage
In the composition,
your eye is drawn to the center,
to the swords, the literal pivot point
between duty and loss.
The whole thing is controlled,
deliberate, organized, the opposite of Rococo
in every possible way.
And then look at the right side
of the painting, the woman.
They're collapsed, weeping, because here's the thing.
One of the Horatii brothers
is married to a woman
from the enemy city.
She's actually the sister
of one of the enemy brothers,
and one of the enemy brothers
is engaged to a Horatii sister.
No matter who wins,
these women lose someone they love.
The men are rigid, vertical,
all straight lines.
The women are curved, soft, crumbling.
Duty on the left, grief
on the right, and the swords
in the center.
The message is brutal and clear.
Duty to the state comes before everything,
before love, before family,
before your own life.
When this painting was exhibited
at the salon,
people wept in front of it.
Not just because it was sad,
because it was powerful.
It felt like a call to action.
And David didn't stop.
In 1780 7, The Death of Socrates.
Socrates, condemned by the Athenian state
for his ideas,
calmly
reaching for the cup of poison
while his students fall apart around him.
The state is killing him,
and he accepts it with perfect calm.
You die for what you believe.
And then, in 1780 9,
the lictors bring to Brutus
the bodies of his sons.
Brutus, the founder of the Roman Republic,
has ordered the execution
of his own sons
for conspiring to restore the monarchy
The bodies are being carried past him.
He doesn't look.
The women scream.
He sits in shadow,
rigid, destroyed, but unbroken.
This painting was displayed at the Salon
just weeks after the storming
of the Bastille.
The Paris prison was attacked
in July 1789,
marked the beginning of the French Revolution.
The story goes that authorities tried
to pull it from the exhibition,
but the crowd demanded it to stay.
whether that happened
exactly as described is debated.
Some historians think
the tale was polished later
to make David seem more heroically embattled.
Regardless, the painting's timing was explosive.
Do you see what's happening?
These aren't just paintings anymore.
A painting about a man
who killed his sons
to protect the Republic, displayed in Paris
in summer of 1789?
That's not art appreciation.
That's a political statement, and
everyone in that room knew it.
David had spent a decade
painting ancient heroes
who sacrificed everything for the state,
and now, in the summer of
1789, the state was being torn apart
and rebuilt.
And David wasn't going
to just paint it,
he was going to join it.
This is where the story goes dark,
and I mean genuinely dark.
Not art world drama dark.
People dying dark.
In 1792, David was elected
to the National Convention, the revolutionary parliament.
He didn't sit with the moderates.
He sat with the Montagrats,
the radicals, the Jacobins.
They were led
by Maximilian Robespierre, the lawyer
who made himself the ideological heart
of the revolution
and who was rapidly becoming
its most feared figure.
And on January twenty-first, seventeen ninety-three,
the day I mentioned
at the beginning,
David voted
for the execution of King Louis XVI.
A painter voted to kill a king.
But he didn't stop there.
David became essentially the revolution's visual authority.
He organized festivals, massive public events meant
to replace Catholic ritual with republican ceremony.
He contributed to the design of uniforms
and public imagery.
He was deeply involved
in shaping what the revolution looked like,
and in a world before photography,
before television,
that meant he had real influence
over what people believed about it.
He was close to Robespierre,
the radical Jacobin leader.
Very close.
He reportedly said to him,
"If you drink hemlock,
I will drink it with you."
That's not a casual friendship.
That's a pact.
He was actively involved
in the revolutionary government,
sitting on the Committee of General Security,
putting his name on documents
that led to people being arrested, tried, and executed.
was
one of many people
who signed, not acting alone,
but consider what that means
for the man
who painted the death of Socrates.
You remember that painting, Socrates
in his last moments,
calmly reaching for the cup of poison
while his students fall apart around him?
Socrates was condemned by the Athenian state
for refusing to abandon his ideas.
That's the subject David chose to paint
and made beautiful,
a man killed by the state.
And now, David was the state.
His name was on the paperwork.
The tension between the ideals he painted
and the reality he served is staggering.
In July 1793, a shocking event
in revolutionary Paris gave rise to
one of the century's most famous paintings.
Jean-Paul Marat was a revolutionary journalist,
a radical.
He had a skin condition
that forced him to spend hours
in a medicinal bath,
where he would write, receive visitors,
and conduct business.
On July 13th, 1793,
a young woman named Charlotte Corday
talked her way into his apartment,
claiming to have information about counter-revolutionary plots.
Marat received her
while sitting in his bath.
She pulled out a knife
and stabbed him in the chest.
He died almost immediately.
According to accounts
that have been passed down,
though some historians treat this with caution,
David had visited Marat
the day before.
He knew the bath,
the setup, the man,
and when he heard the news,
he went to work immediately.
Look at it.
Marat is slumped in his bath.
His head is wrapped in a cloth.
His skin is pale, almost glowing.
His face is calm, peaceful.
He looks like he's sleeping.
He looks like Christ
taken down from the cross.
But I'll get to that
in a sec.
In his left hand, a letter.
Corday, Marat's murderer,
did use a letter
to get into the apartment,
but this isn't that letter.
David wrote those words himself.
They make
Marat look like a man killed
while helping someone in need.
David put it in his hand
on purpose as part of the myth
he was building.
On the floor, the knife, bloodied,
and on the wooden block
besides the bath,
the block Marat used as a desk,
David carved 2 words.
To Marat from David.
He signed the painting into the painting.
It's a dedication, a memorial,
and a political act.
Now, here's what I need you
to sit with.
This painting is propaganda.
It absolutely is.
David has taken a man
who was, by many accounts, paranoid, cruel,
and responsive for stirring up mob violence
And turned him into a saint.
The bath is clean, the body idealized.
The composition is borrowed directly
from Christian art, specifically the Pietà,
which is a famous image
of Mary holding the body of Jesus.
You know this Michelangelo's famous sculpture?
Do you see it?
That arrangement, that specific quality of grief
held perfectly still.
David took it and transplanted it into a bathtub in Paris.
Marat as the Revolution's crucified Christ.
David made this painting
to serve the revolution,
to turn a murderer
into a martyr,
to make
you feel something specific, grief, outrage, devotion
to the cause.
It's propaganda and it's a masterpiece.
Both are true at the same time,
and that tension
is what makes David so important
and so unsettling.
He painted virtue. He preached sacrifice. And he signed the warrants that sent people to die.
The revolution gave David everything: power, purpose,
a reason to paint
Now, it was about
to take it all back.
It couldn't last.
The revolution, like all revolutions,
started eating its own.
On July 27th, 1794, Robespierre,
the radical Jacobin leader, was overthrown, arrested,
executed the next day, and soon
after, they came for David.
He was arrested, imprisoned.
He came very close
to the guillotine himself, the same guillotine
he had helped send others to.
His students lobbied for his release.
It took months.
And in prison, he did something remarkable.
He painted himself not as a hero,
not as a martyr,
not as someone Roman or Greek,
just himself.
A middle-aged man with a swollen cheek.
he had a facial tumor
that distorted his features.
Holding a palette, looking out at you
with an expression that's hard to read.
Surprise?
Confusion?
Honesty?
It might be the most intimate thing
he ever painted
because it wasn't for anyone.
It wasn't for the salon
or for the revolution.
It was just a man
in a cell looking at himself.
And don't ask me
how he got painting materials in prison.
After his release,
he said he had been deceived
by the mask of patriotism.
Was he?
Was he really deceived,
or was he just saying
what he needed to say to survive?
That's one of the great unanswerable questions
about David, and I think
the answer might be both.
He was a true believer
who was also very good in surviving.
People are complicated.
And then he met Napoleon.
It was 1797.
Napoleon was a young general, already famous,
already radiating that kind of charisma
that makes painter reach for their brushes.
David met him and wrote,
Oh, my friends,
what a beautiful head he has.
It is pure, it is great.
It is as beautiful as the antique.
As beautiful as the antique.
There it is again.
David looked at a living, breathing military
commander and saw a Greek statue.
He couldn't help himself.
And Napoleon, a master of image
and spectacle, saw in David
exactly what he needed.
The greatest painter of his time, ready
to turn him into a living legend.
Okay.Napoleon crossing the Alps, 1801.
You know this image.
Even if
you never been into an art museum,
you know this image.
Napoleon on a rearing
white horse, cape flowing, arm pointing
forward, the names of Hannibal and Charlemagne
carved into the rocks below him,
As if to say
he belongs among them.
I've seen this painting in person,
and the first thing
that hits you is the scale.
If you see it on a screen,
it's completely different from how
people back at the time felt when
they saw it in front of them.
Like, this painting is about this size,
you just stand
in front of it, and you feel
that you're looking at something amazing.
I can't explain it.
You, you have to experience it,
'cause I was really surprised
to feel that way.
Okay, back to the story.
The painting is huge.
You stand in front of it, and
you feel small, which is, of course,
exactly the point.
Napoleon
asked to be painted calm
on a spirited horse.
David delivered.
Here's the thing, though.
The real crossing was difficult, cold,
and unglamorous.
Napoleon rode a mule for much
of it, led by a local guide.
David wasn't painting what happened.
He was painting
what Napoleon wanted to believe about himself.
The heroic version.
The myth.
Nobody remembers the mule.
Everyone remembers this.
And then there's the coronation.
1805 to 1807.
Over 30 feet wide.
Napoleon crowning Josephine at Notre Dame,
surrounded by hundreds of figures.
David was there in person,
sketching the ceremony.
But he rearranged reality.
Look, see that woman in the balcony?
That's Napoleon's mother, Leticia.
She's prominently placed, watching proudly.
Except she wasn't there.
She refused to come.
David painted her in anyway
because Napoleon wanted her there.
The painting isn't a record
of what happened.
It's a record
of what should have happened
According to the man in charge.
After Napoleon's final defeat in 1815,
the Bourbon monarchy was restored, and
they had a long memory.
David had voted to execute their king
in 1793.
That was 22 years ago.
They hadn't forgotten.
He was exiled, banned from France
as a king killer.
He moved to Brussels and kept painting,
but the work got softer, less urgent.
The fire was going out.
He died in Brussels
on December 29th, 1825,
at the age of 77.
France refused
to allow his body to return.
The man who had
been the most powerful artist
in the country,
who had shaped the visual identity
of the revolution, of Napoleon,
of an entire era,
was buried in a foreign city.
He's still there.
So, what did
David leave behind?
A movement, a set of rules,
and an institution, the Académie Royale,
that would enforce those rules
for the next 50 years.
His greatest student, Ingres,
became the guardian of that legacy.
He spent his entire career
defending classical drawing, insisting that discipline
and line were the foundation of everything.
The Académie backed him.
For decades, the world David built held.
So here's
where I want to leave you.
David understood something fundamental about images.
They aren't just decoration, they're arguments.
A painting can make you believe something.
It can make an idea
feel noble, inevitable, even heroic.
his style
helped make that power possible
The clean lines, the stark compositions,
the restrained, controlled color.
Everything is clear, deliberate, and serious.
Nothing is accidental.
The paintings feel certain
about what they are saying,
and that certainty is persuasive.
And the images themself did real work.
The Oath of the Horatii
didn't just show Roman virtue,
it presented a model
of duty and sacrifice.
The Death of Marat didn't simply show
a political killing, it transformed Marat
into a martyr of the revolution.
Napoleon crossing the Alps
didn't document an event. It constructed Napoleon's image of leadership.
That’s David’s real legacy. Not just a style, and not only a school of followers but a demonstration of how powerful images can shape political imagination.
But the more interesting part
of David's story isn't the propaganda,
it's the man behind it.
David painted virtue, duty, and sacrifice,
and he seemed to have genuinely believe
in those ideals.
At the same time,
he lived at the center of power
during one of the most violent
and chaotic periods in French history.
That combination was rare.
An artist who wasn't just observing events,
but helping shape how
they were seen and remembered.
And that may be
what makes him so remarkable.
Not just a great painter,
but an artist
whose images helped define an era.
But not everyone accepted
what David had built
Not everyone thought paintings
should be lessons in virtue
or that reason should rule everything art
could be.
One painter born in seventeen ninety-eight,
just a few years after the Terror,
the revolution's most violent period,
was about
to blow the whole thing up.
Was about to blow the whole thing
up with color, with chaos,
with a trip to North Africa
that changed the way he saw everything.
His name was Eugène Delacroix,
and his story starts
with a shipwreck, a madman,
and a raft full of corpses.
That's next time.
ביי.